Curriculum Vitae

Joseph M. Kush

Bloomberg School of Public Health . Johns Hopkins University

624 N Broadway Room 841 ° Baltimore, MD 21205

(412) 526-5507 ° jkush1@jhu.edu

EDUCATION

Ph.D.	2021	University of Virginia Educational Psychology – Research, Statistics and Evaluation Advisors: Timothy R. Konold and Catherine P. Bradshaw
B.S.	2016	Syracuse University Psychology – Minors in Applied Statistics, Philosophy

PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS

2021 -	Postdoctoral Fellowship, Department of Mental Health, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Advisors: Elizabeth A. Stuart and Rashelle J. Musci
2016 - 2021	Research and Teaching Assistant, University of Virginia School of Education and Human Development
2014 - 2015	Research Assistant, Syracuse University S.I. Newhouse School of Public Communications
2011 - 2016	Research Assistant, Syracuse University Department of Psychology

HONORS AND AWARDS

2021-2023	Prevention Science Early Career Reviewer Program
2020	University of Virginia Outstanding Graduate Teaching Assistant Award
2016 - 2021	University of Virginia Graduate Fellowship
2012 - 2016	Syracuse University Dean's List

Personal Statement

I am currently a postdoctoral fellow in the Department of Mental Health at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, working alongside Dr. Elizabeth Stuart and Dr. Rashelle Kush – October 2021

Musci. My training is focused in the areas of statistical methods for causal inference and data harmonization, including application to topics in mental health and education. My research is primarily interested in improving statistical methods and research designs for the social sciences. Often utilizing Monte Carlo simulation studies, this has included work on multilevel measurement models, propensity score methods for causal-inference in intervention implementation, and research design considerations such as statistical power for clustered randomized trials. I have also worked closely alongside substantive researchers in the areas of educational and behavioral interventions and evaluation, racial disproportionality in disciplinary outcomes, and measurement related to social, emotional, and behavioral assessments.

SCHOLARLY ACTIVITY

Publications

Peer Reviewed

- Bradshaw, C.P., Pas, E. T., Musci, R. J., **Kush, J. M.**, & Ryoo, J. H. (2021). Leveraging policy to improve behavioral and academic outcomes through School-wide Positive Behavioral Interventions and Supports. *Prevention Science*, 22(7), 986-1000. https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs11121-021-01257-0
- **Kush, J. M.**, Konold, T. R., & Bradshaw, C.P. (2021). The sampling ratio in multilevel structural equation models: Considerations to inform study design. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. https://doi.org/10.1177/00131644211020112
- **Kush, J. M.**, Konold, T. K., & Bradshaw, C. P. (2021). Statistical power for randomized controlled trials with clusters of varying size. *The Journal of Experimental Education*. https://doi.org/10.1080/00220973.2021.1873089
- Larson, K., Pas, E. T., Bottiani, J., **Kush, J. M.**, & Bradshaw, C. P. (2020). A multidimensional and multilevel examination of student engagement and teachers' use of classroom management practices. *Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions*, 23(3), 149-162. https://doi.org/10.1177/1098300720929352
- Bradshaw, C. P., & **Kush**, **J. M.** (2019). Teacher observation of classroom adaptation-checklist: Measuring Children's Social, Emotional, and Behavioral Functioning. *Children & Schools*, 42(1), 29-40. https://doi.org/10.1093/cs/cdz022
- Larson, K. E., Bottiani, J. H., Pas, E. T., **Kush, J. M.**, & Bradshaw, C. P. (2019). A multilevel analysis of racial discipline disproportionality: A focus on student perceptions of academic engagement and disciplinary environment. *Journal of School Psychology*, 77, 152-167. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsp.2019.09.003
- Morin, H. K., Bradshaw, C. P., & **Kush, J. M.** (2018). Adjustment outcomes of victims of cyberbullying: The role of personal and contextual factors. *Journal of School Psychology*, 70, 74–88. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsp.2018.07.002

Kush – October 2021

Manuscripts under review

Henderson, L. J., Bottiani, J., **Kush, J. M.**, & Bradshaw, C. P. (Under review, 2021). The discipline gap in context: The role of school racial and ethnic diversity in out-of-school suspensions.

- **Kush, J. M.**, Badillo-Goicoechea, E., Musci, R. J., & Stuart, E. A. (Under review, 2021). Teacher mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: Informing policies to support teacher well-being and effective teaching practices.
- Bradshaw, C. P., Katrina, J. D., **Kush, J. M.**, & Lindstrom-Johnson, S. (Under review, 2021). Planning for a crisis, but preparing for everyday: What predicts schools' preparedness to respond to a school safety crisis?
- Bloomfield-Clagett, B., Greenstein, D. K., **Kush, J. M.**, Musci, R. J., Zarate, C. A., & Ballard, E. (Under review, 2021). Predictors of suicidal ideation trajectories in the Sequenced Treatment Alternatives to Relieve Depression (STAR*D) study.
- Brown, J. T., Volk, F., & **Kush, J. M.** (Under review, 2021). How the COVID pandemic differentially impacted retention for residential and online students: Implications for financial aid policy and practice.

Manuscripts in progress

- Bottiani, J. H., **Kush, J. M.**, McDaniel, H., Pas, E. T., & Bradshaw, C. P. (In progress, 2021). Effect of Positive Behavioral Interventions and Supports on school discipline disproportionality: A quasi-experimental study.
- Brown, J. T., Volk, F., & **Kush, J. M.** (In progress, 2021). Inequalities in higher education: The interaction of race, socioeconomic status, and residence hall design on academic outcomes.
- Bradshaw, C. P., **Kush, J. M.**, Braun, S. S., & Barton, E. A. (In progress, 2021). Understanding the perceived impact of the COVID-19 pivot to on-line instruction on teacher and administrator stress.
- **Kush, J. M.**, Masyn, K. E., Amin-Esmaeili, M., Susukida, R., Wilcox, H. C., & Musci, R. J. (In progress, 2021). Utilizing moderated nonlinear factor analysis models for integrative data analysis: A tutorial.
- **Kush, J. M.**, Pas, E. T., Musci, R. J., & Bradshaw, C. P. (In progress, 2021). Covariate balance for observational scale-ups: A comparison of matching and weighting.

Conference Presentations and Posters

Presentations

Bradshaw, C. P., **Kush, J. M.**, Braun, S. S., & Barton, E. A. (February, 2022). Educator stress, coping, and well-being during the COVID-19 pandemic. National Association of School Psychologists, Boston, MA.

Kush – October 2021 4

Kush, J. M., Badillo-Goicoechea, E., Musci, R. J., & Stuart, E. A. (September, 2021). Teacher mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: Informing policies to support teacher well-being and effective teaching practices. Society for Research on Educational Effectiveness, Arlington, VA.

- Bradshaw, C. P., **Kush, J. M.**, Braun, S. S., & Barton, E. A. (June, 2021). Understanding the perceived impact of COVID-19 on teacher and administrator stress and the social-emotional functioning of their students. Society for Prevention Research, Virtual Meeting.
- **Kush, J. M.**, Konold, T. R., & Bradshaw, C. P. (April 2021). The role of sampling ratio in multilevel structural equation models. American Educational Research Association, Virtual Meeting.
- Musci, R. J., & **Kush**, **J. M.** (May 2020). Class enumeration in latent class analysis with nested data. Society for Prevention Research, Washington, D.C.
- **Kush, J. M.** (May 2019). Unbalanced cluster sizes and variation in sampling in cluster randomized controlled trials: What's the impact on power? Society for Prevention Research, San Francisco, CA.
- Ryoo, J. H., Pas, E. T., **Kush, J. M.**, Musci, R., & Bradshaw, C. P. (May 2018). Efficiency of propensity score methods in longitudinal and multilevel data via monte carlo simulation. Society for Prevention Research, Washington, D.C.
- Ryoo, J. H., Kush, **J. M.**, Pas, E. T., Musci, R., & Bradshaw, C. P. (May 2018). Investigation of propensity score matching paradox in longitudinal data. Society for Prevention Research, Washington, D.C.
- Bradshaw, C. P., Ryoo, J. H., Pas, E. T., **Kush, J. M.**, & Musci, R. (May 2018). Impacts of statemandated pbis implementation on behavior and achievement outcomes. Society for Prevention Research, Washington, D.C.
- Ryoo, J. H., Bradshaw, C. P., & **Kush, J. M.** (July 2017). Propensity score analysis using superlearner for longitudinal data. Psychometric Society, Zürich, Switzerland.

Posters

- **Kush, J. M.** (June 2020). Statistical power for randomized trials with clusters of varying size. Modern Modeling Methods, Storrs, CT.
- **Kush, J. M.**, & Catherine, C. P. (March 2019). The TOCA-C: An efficient approach to measuring children's social, emotional, and behavioral functioning by teachers. Society for Research in Child Development, Baltimore, MD.
- Ryoo, J. H., **Kush, J. M.**, Pas, E. T., Musci, R., & Bradshaw, C. P. (May 2018). Power analysis in multilevel data with variability in the level 1 units. Society for Prevention Research, Washington, DC.

Kush – October 2021 5

TEACHING AND RESEARCH GRANT EXPERIENCE

Teaching Experience

1. Primary Instructor for EDLF 2080, Fundamentals of Health and Social Science Statistics, Fall 2019, University of Virginia

- Created all course material, including homework, exams, and in-class assignments for students. Responsible for teaching and grading undergraduate students. Undergraduate-level course.
- 2. Teaching Assistant for EDLF 8360 Multilevel Modeling in Education Research, Fall 2018, University of Virginia
 - Created in-class assignments for students. Held office hours for material review, provided support for homework or other in-class assignments, as well as provided assistance for final projects reports. Graduate-level course.
- 3. Teaching assistant for EDLF 7420 Quantitative Methods II: General Linear Models, Spring 2018, University of Virginia
 - Held office hours for material review, provided support for homework or other in-class assignments, as well as provided assistance for final projects reports. Graduate-level course.

Research Grant Experience

1. Evaluating Maryland State Policies to Improve School Climate

Funding Institute of Education Sciences (IES)

ID R305H150027

Role Research Associate (PIs: Bradshaw, C. P., Alexander, A., & Pas, E. T.)

Period 07/2015 - 06/2020

Total \$2,756,311

Topic Assessing the implementation fidelity and effectives of Positive Behavioral

Interventions and Supports (PBIS), a school-wide intervention mandated

throughout the state of Maryland.

2. Implementing State-Level Policy Reform to Eliminate School Discipline Disparities: A Mixed Methods Examination

Funding William T. Grant Foundation

Role Research Associate (PIs: Bottiani, J. H., & Bradshaw, C. P.)

Period 04/2018 - 03/2021

Total \$150,403

Topic To evaluate the effectiveness of a state-level policy to reduce discipline disparities

for Black youth.

Kush – October 2021 6

3. Examining the Association between Residence Hall Design, Student Socialization Processes, and Academic Outcomes

Funding Association of College and University Housing Officers - International (ACUHO-

I)

Role Co-Investigator (PI: Brown, J.)

Period 07/2020 - 12/2021

Total \$5,000

Topic Investigating interactions among residence hall type, race, and hall-specific

socialization processes related to first-year student outcomes in the form of

student interactions and student learning.

4. Netting Prevention Intervention Butterfly Effects: An Integrative Data Analysis Investigating the Long-term and Cross-over Effects of Randomized, School-based Prevention Programs on Adult Mental Health

Funding National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)

ID R01MH122214

Role Research Associate (PIs: Musci, R. J., & Wilcox, H. C.)

Period 12/2019 – 11/2022

Total \$514,525

To link and harmonize data from six randomized controlled trials with preventive

interventions to understand long-term impacts on mental health outcomes through early adulthood, including suicidal behaviors, depression and anxiety symptoms

and diagnoses, and psychosis symptoms.

5. Addressing Suicide Research Gaps: Understanding Mortality Outcomes in the Mid-Atlantic Region

Funding National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)

ID R56MH117560

Role Statistical Analyst (PIs: Kharrazi, H. H. K., & Wilcox, H. C.)

Period 09/2019 - 09/2020

Total \$492,000

Topic Conducting data linkage and informatics approaches to utilize existing resources

to improve suicide risk identification and prevention.

Statistical Software Training

Advanced: Mplus, R, Stata, HLM8, jMetrik, WinBUGS, and SPSS.

Learning: flexMIRT, MLwiN and Stan.

Kush – October 2021

SERVICE

Ad-Hoc Reviewing Activities

Prevention Science, 2021-Global Mental Health, 2021-

Conference Reviewing Activities

American Educational Research Association, 2021-American Educational Research Association Division D Graduate Student Council In-Progress Research Gala, 2021 Hunter Student Research Conference, 2021 Curry Research Conference, 2018-2020

Profession Affiliations

American Educational Research Association (AERA, Division D) American Psychological Association (APA, Division 5) Society for Prevention Research (SPR) Society for Research on Child Development (SRCD) Society for Research on Educational Effectiveness (SREE)